Austryn Wainhouse Papers
Austryn Wainhouse Papers
1934-2007
Wainhouse, Austryn.
14 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts and memorabilia of the American author and translator of de Sade.
4145807
Biographical History
Austryn Wainhouse (1927-2014) was an American author, publisher and translator, particularly of French works. He is best known for his translation into English of the complete works of the Marquis de Sade.
Born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1927, Wainhouse graduated from Harvard University and then traveled in Europe, eventually settling in Paris with his wife Mary ("Muffie") in 1949. There he worked for Maurice Girodias at Olympia Press, for whom he produced the first unexpurgated English translation of de Sade's Justine (1953), and was an editor of Alexander Trocchi's literary magazine Merlin. His letters from this period suggest that his bohemian lifestyle and political leanings somewhat puzzled his father, a long-time American Foreign Service employee and the author of numerous books on peace and arms control.
By 1960 Wainhouse was divorced and dividing his time between the United States and Europe. In the mid-1960s he began working with avant-garde publishing house Grove Press to produce an English translation of Sade's complete works, including his Letters from Vincennes and from the Bastille. Wainhouse was given the post of Writer-in-Residence at the Jonas Salk Institute in 1971, where his colleagues included physician Jonas Salk and physicist Jacques Monod; in 1972 he won the National Book Award (Translation) for his translation of Monod's Chance and Necessity.
For the next several years he continued writing and translating from his home in Vermont. Then in 1982 he established The Marlboro Press in Marlboro, Vermont, with the goal of publishing English translations of French and Italian works. "[A]s a publisher [I] could pursue no more responsible course and render no service of greater usefulness to the American reading public than to strengthen and multiply its imaginative connections with the rest of the world," he wrote in a brief history of the press. Over the next twenty years the press published more than ninety titles (first under its own imprint and later under the joint imprint of The Marlboro Press/Northwestern University Press), including literary travel, poetry and fiction.
Wainhouse remained good friends with his former wife Mary ("Muffie") and in the late 1990s he and his wife, Deborah Clayton Wainhouse, relocated to Santa Fe, New Mexico where Muffie was living. Muffie died in 2001. Wainhouse's affection for France had never waned, and that same year he and Deborah retired to Uzès in the south of France where he died in 2014.
Wainhouse had three daughters, Cassandra, Melissa, and Suzannah, and one son, Henry.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Austryn Wainhouse Papers consists of calendars, correspondence, diaries, financial material, manuscripts, memorabilia, notebooks, Sade material, and a small amount of miscellanea. The collection contains both personal and professional material and spans Wainhouse's entire career, with particular emphasis on his early work including his translations of the Marquis de Sade.
Calendars consists of 31 small desk calendars, spanning thirty years, with Wainhouse's notes.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters (Wainhouse often made carbon copies of his letters, even to friends and family). Notable correspondents include Simone de Beauvoir, Alain Accardo, Georges Bataille, Samuel Beckett, Albert Guerard. The most extensive correspondence is with Dick Seaver, his editor for the Sade books at Grove Press; with British poet Christopher Logue, a close friend with whom he corresponded for more than forty years; and with his wife Mary (Muffie).
Diaries consist of a variety of bound volumes, mostly untitled, spanning about forty years. The first volume includes Wainhouse's pithy observations on his Navy experience and clippings of some of his columns. Later volumes cover a summer in Mallorca (Majorca), a year in Geneva, and "Years with Michelle."
Financial material includes ledgers in which Wainhouse entered his translations and fees, royalty statements from several publishers, and some miscellaneous notes.
Manuscripts, one of the largest series, includes original work as well as translations. Original work includes essays (topics include Baudelaire and "Negroness"), short stories (e.g., "The Prince of Janitzio") and novels (Aftosa, Artra, Hedyphagetica, There Comes a Youth), many of which were apparently never published. Also here is Wainhouse's master's thesis on E.M. Forster. Translations include works by Georges Bataille, Maurice Blanchot, Pierre Jean Jouve, Aleksandra Kroh. Formats include handwritten manuscripts, typescripts, typescript carbons, and others, many with annotations and corrections.
Memorabilia contains a large number of photographs, two boxes of slides, a few negatives, a scrapbook, and some assorted paper memorabilia (membership cards, etc.) Nearly all of the photos are candid shots of Wainhouse, family, friends, houses, scenes in Europe, etc. They have been sleeved for protection, but since most are undated/unlabeled and they arrived in a single box without any organization, no attempt has been made to arrange or categorize them and they remain in random order.
The collection contains more than twenty spiral Notebooks, though not all are found in this series. In some cases, such as the Juliette notebooks (see Sade material below) they were clearly either translations or drafts of original work; these have been filed under Manuscripts or Sade material, depending on their content. What remains in this series are notebooks whose contents either could not be identified, such as one containing practice exercises in Greek and another labeled "Traveler from Peking."
Sade material represents nearly a quarter of the collection. The bulk of this series consists of manuscripts and typescripts of Wainhouse's translations. There are 13 spiral notebooks filled with Wainhouse's original handwritten translation of Justine, numerous drafts of Letters from Vincennes, drafts of Klossowski's Sade mon prochain, and a handwritten translation of Philosophia dans la boudoir (Philosophy in the Bedroom). Also included here are original works by Wainhouse, such as his essay "On translating Sade," the foreword to Juliette Book III, and a "Translator's preface." There are two folders of publicity, both from Grove and from the press (reviews, articles, etc.), and a few miscellaneous items such as the typescript of "The Boudoir Philosophers," a stage version of Philosophy in the Bedroom written by Eric Kahane.
The few items of Miscellany at the end of the collection consists of photopies of two published novels and a random assortment of clippings and printed material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Calendars and diaries are arranged chronologically. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and, within that, chronologically. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title, with all translations grouped alphabetically under that subheading. Memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type but no further arrangement has been attempted and photographs are in no particular order. Sade material is arranged alphabetically by title or type of material; the folders of publicity have been sorted by year only.
Related Material
See also the
Grove Press Records
.
Separated Material
A number of published books have been removed from the collection for cataloging. A complete list of these items is available on request, or you may search for "Austryn Wainhouse" as a keyword.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- French; Publishing, printing and book arts; Accardo, Alain.; Bataille, Georges, 1897-1962.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.; Blackburn, Paul.; Blanchot, Maurice.; de Wet, Louis.; Froshaug, Anthony.; Guérard, Albert J. (Albert Joseph), 1914-; Hyvernaud, Andrée.; Hyvernaud, Georges.; Klossowski, Pierre.; Lilienthal, David Eli, 1899-1981.; Logue, Christopher, 1926-2011.; Malina, Judith, 1926-; Monod, Jacques.; Sade, marquis de, 1740-1814 -- Translations into English.; Seaver, Richard.; Spingarn, Lawrence Perry, 1917-; Trocchi, Alexander, 1925-1984.; Wainhouse, Austryn.; Wainhouse, David W.; Wainhouse, Mary.; Wyckoff, Alexander.; Grove Press.; The Marlboro Press.; Merlin.; Authors, American.; Authors, French.; French literature -- 20th century -- Translations into English.; Publishers and publishing -- Vermont.; Small presses -- Vermont.; Translations -- Publishing.; Translators.; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Manuscripts for publication.; Manuscripts (document genre); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Authors.; Translators.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2013.
Inventory
- Calendars
  - Calendars, 1963-1989; 27 volumes (Box 1)
  - Calendars, 1990-1993; 4 volumes (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - —, Alex [Trocchi?], 1954-1957; 1960; from AW to "Alex" with no surname; possibly Alex Trocchi (Box 3)
  - —, Jack, 1954-1955; 1977,; 1979 (Box 3)
  - —, Jean-Paul and Dimitry, 1974; 2003 (Box 3)
  - —, John [Hunt?], 1951-1952; 1956 (Box 3)
  - —, "M" [Michele?], circa 1959; in English and French (Box 3)
  - —, Pat / Patrick / Padraig, 1954; 1956-1958,; 1972,; 1974; may be several different people (Box 3)
  - Academie d'Orleans-Tours, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Accardo, Alain, 2005 (Box 3)
    See also Manuscripts: Translations: Letter to my comrades on the left (Accardo).
  - Aldington, Richard, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, 1971-1974; 1978; bulk relates to Monod translation (Box 3)
    See also Financial: Royalty statements, Alfred A. Knopf.
  - Arcade Press (Dick Seaver), 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Atlantic Monthly, See Davison, Peter.
  - Bataille, Georges, 1952-1960; 1967,; 1999; correspondence; clippings about (Box 3)
  - de Beauvoir, Simone, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1952-1953; 1956; includes correspondence between Beckett and Alex Trocchi (Box 3)
  - Beiles, Sinclair, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Berke, Joseph, 1967; Instutute for Phenomenological Studies; Dialectic of Liberation (Box 3)
  - di Bernardi, Dominic, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Berry, Wallace and Maxine, undated (Box 3)
  - Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation / Tribunal, 1966-1967; includes printed material from the Foundation, bios of members, clippings, etc.; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1957-1958; 1970 (Box 3)
  - Blanchot, Maurice, 1952-1956; undated (Box 3)
  - Bowles, Pat, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Briault, Mary, See Wainhouse, Mary (Muffie).
  - Burnell, Robert (Bob) and Connie, 1970; 1975 (Box 3)
  - Burnett, Virgil, 2005; see also (Box 3)
    See also correspondence folder in Manuscripts: Translations: Letter to my comrades on the left (Accardo).
  - Carson Chemical Company, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Chelsea Green Publishing (Margo Baldwin), 2007; relates to translation of Kempf book (Box 3)
  - China, 1961; 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Clemens, Cyril, 1971; dubbing AW a "Knight of Mark Twain" (Box 3)
  - Cocteau, Jean, undated; fragment of letter, with signature (Box 3)
  - Cohen, Albert, "Coheniana" sent to AW by Ann McGarrell; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Cohen, Stanley (Weil, Gotshal and Manges), 1969 (Box 4)
  - College applications, 1969-1971; letters to various colleges about teaching positions (Box 4)
  - Creeley, Bob, 1955; 1968,; 1972,; 1974 (Box 4)
  - Cuba trip, 1967-1968; includes correspondence with Barney Rossett, Dick Seaver, Dionys Mascolo (Box 4)
  - Dalkey Archives Press, 1996; 2005 (Box 4)
  - Davison, Peter, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Deberdt-Malaquais, Elisabeth, 1967; relates to rights for extract from Thomas l'Obscur (Box 4)
  - Dixon, Keith, 2001; 2003 (Box 4)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Esquire magazine, 1965-1966; relates to "On translating Sade" (Box 4)
  - Feshbach, Sid, 2001-2002; 2007 (Box 4)
  - Froshaug, Anthony, 1956; 1959 (Box 4)
  - George Weidenfeld & Nicolson, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Giono, Jean, bibliography of works (Box 4)
  - Goodwin, Clive, 1966; 1970,; 1975 (Box 4)
  - Grove Press, 1955; 1966-1972,; 1975,; 1980-1981; Barney Rossett, Fred Jordan, Marilynn Meeker (Box 4)
    See also Cuba trip; Seaver, Dick; Financial: Royalty statements, Grove Press.
  - Guerard, Albert and Maclen, 1954-1961; 1968-1969,; 1974,; undated; includes obituary and photocopies of some of Guerard's writings; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Guerin, Daniel, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Hazo, Samuel, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - Hopper, John (Jack), AMS Press, 1969-1971; 1974,; 1977,; 1996 (Box 4)
  - Hunt, John, 1956-1959; 1966-1973,; 1982-1983,; 1997,; 2001,; 2003 (Box 4)
  - Hyvernaud, Andrée, 1995; 1997,; undated; includes two manuscripts by Georges Hyvernaud, Silhouettes (illustrated by Victor Ruiz-Huidobro) and Suivre la Guide (Box 4)
  - John Calder Publishers, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Johns Hopkins Press, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Johnson, Ben, 1955; 1957 (Box 4)
  - Jonathan Cape, 1971-1972; relates to Ma Mere (Box 4)
  - Jordan, Ken, See Grove Press.
  - Kahane, Eric, See Sade: Miscellaneous: The Boudoir Philosophers.
  - Kirk, Emily, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Klossowski, Pierre, 1950-1951; 1955,; 1960-1961,; 1965,; 1969-1970; relates to Sade (Box 4)
    See also Sade: Translations: Sade mon prochain.
  - Kolko, Gabriel, 1968-1989 (Box 4)
  - Lecture correspondence, 1979; various colleges (Box 4)
  - Legman, G., 1955; 1968 (Box 4)
  - Lilienthal, David, 1966-1976; 1979 (Box 4)
  - Logue, Christopher, 1956-1985; 1994-2004,; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Malina diary project (Brazilian Diary of Judith Malina), 1981; includes correspondence with Malina (Box 5)
  - Marion Boyars Publishers, 1986-1988; includes photocopy of Ma Mere and other pieces with AW's corrections (Box 5)
  - Marlboro College, 1971-1973; 1978-1981 (Box 5)
  - Marlboro Press
    See also Northwestern University Press.
    - Benedetti, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1995-1998; 2001 (Box 5)
    - Gozzano book (David Marinelli), 1993 (Box 5)
    - Hans Christian Anderson, photocopy of "A Visit to North Africa" (Box 5)
    - History, archives, 2000; includes brief history of press by AW (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1992; 1995-2002,; 2006,; undated (Box 5)
  - Marquand, John, 1965; 1967,; 1971,; 1977 (Box 5)
  - Mascolo, Dionys, See Cuba trip.
  - McGarrell, Ann, 1999-2003; includes translations of works by Melania Mazzucco (Box 5)
    See also Marlboro Press.
  - Medical papers, 1991; 1998,; 2005 (Box 5)
  - Meeker, Marilynn, See Grove Press.
  - Merlin, 1954-1956 (Box 5)
  - Millet, Richard, 1997; photocopied clippings relating to "L'amour des trois soeurs piale" (Box 5)
  - Monod, Jacques, 1970-1972; see also (Box 5)
    See also Alfred A. Knopf.
  - National Book Award, 1972 (Box 6)
  - New Directions Press, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
  - The New York Times, 1965; letter to the editor from AW (Box 6)
  - Norse, Harold, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Northwestern University Press, 1998; 2000-2006; see also The Marlboro Press (Box 6)
  - O'Donoghue, Derek and Betsy, 1960; 1980 (Box 6)
  - PEN newsletter, 1970; 1972; includes "Translator's Bill of Rights" (Box 6)
  - Penguin Press, 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Peyre, Henri, 1966; 1970 (Box 6)
  - Pons, Louis, 1962; 1966,; 2004; includes exhibit catalog, AW's notes on Pons (Box 6)
  - Property lists, 1956; undated; includes two attached letters, from "Duncan" and "Bill" (Box 6)
  - Publishers, various, 1964-1965; 1998; about Sade (Box 6)
  - de Rache, Andre (editor), 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Robling, Mary Jo, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Roditi, Edouard, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Rosenbaum, Lisa, 1960; 1997 (Box 6)
  - Rossett, Barney, See Grove Press.
  - San Lazzaro, G. (XXe Siecle), 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Schulson, Hyman, 1958-1960; attorney (Box 6)
  - Seaver, Dick, 1955; 1958-1972,; 1979-1980,; 1998,; undated; includes substantial Sade material; 3 folders (Box 6)
    See also Cuba trip.
  - Shattuck, Roger, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Shepley, John, undated (Box 6)
  - Skira, M. and Mme., 1955 (Box 6)
  - Slade, Brenda, 1974; formerly Brenda Parkhouse (Box 6)
  - Slocombe, Lorna (Estate of), 1999 (Box 6)
  - Smith, Bill, 1956; undated (Box 6)
  - Spingarn, Lawrence (Larry), 1961; 1969,; 1974-1975,; 1981-1982; includes thoughts on translating Portuguese verse; typescript of short story, "The Ambassador" (Box 6)
  - Taylor, John, 2004; 2006 (Box 6)
  - Trocchi, Alex, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    See also —, Alex, some of which may be Trocchi.
  - U.S. Navy, 1946; evaluation of AW's performance as officer candidate (Box 6)
  - University of Angers, 1974 (Box 6)
  - University of Nice, 1973; includes c.v. (Box 6)
  - Vogue, 1967; relates to Bertrand Russell Tribunal article (Box 6)
  - Wainhouse, Cassandra (daughter), 1998; 2000 (Box 6)
  - Wainhouse, David and Katherine (parents), 1956; 1960-1963,; 1971 (Box 6)
  - Wainhouse, Jon (brother)
    - About, 1946; letter from AW to a Mr MacCubbin (Box 6)
    - Drawings by, 1934; 1945-1946,; undated (Box 6)
  - Wainhouse, Mary (Muffie), 1950-1951; 1954-1962,; 1965,; 1977,; 1997-1998,; 2001,; undated; incoming and outgoing; main correspondent is AW, but there are also a few letters to and from others; last folder includes obituary and text of AW's eulogy at her funeral (as Mary Briault); 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Waldberg, Patrick, 1956; 1965,; 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - de Wet, Louis, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Whalen, Polly, 1975; 1977 (Box 7)
  - White, Gary Scott, 2002-2003; includes photograph (Box 7)
  - Wieck, Fred, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Wright, Ellen, 1957-1958; 1960 (Box 7)
  - Wyckoff, Alexander, circa 1955-1982; majority are undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z, first name only (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, unidentified (Box 7)
- Diaries
  - [untitled], Dec 1944 - Feb 1952; first volume includes AW's thoughts on his Navy experience and clippings of his work; 9 volumes (Box 8)
  - [untitled], Feb 1952 - Feb 1955; 3 volumes (Box 9)
  - Mallorca notes, 1955; summer (June, July, August); 1 volume (Box 9)
  - Geneva, Feb 1955 - Jun 1956; 1 volume (Box 9)
  - [untitled], Jun 1956 - May 1958; 2 volumes (Box 9)
  - Paris, Jun 1958 - May 1961; 1 volume (Box 9)
  - Years with Michelle, [1958-1961?]; appears to describe the years 1958 to 1961, but no indication of when it was written; 1 volume (Box 9)
  - [untitled], Christmas 1973 - Feb 1981; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Black notebook about Elsa relationship, 1981; mostly blank, only about 8 pages are used; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - [untitled], Feb 1984 - Oct 1984; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - [untitled], undated; 1 volume (Box 10)
- Financial
  - Ledgers, 1948-1959; 4 volumes (Box 10)
  - Ledgers, 1960-1968; 1973-1975; 3 volumes (Box 11)
  - Royalty statements, Alfred A. Knopf, 1970-1984 (Box 11)
  - Royalty statements, Grove Press, 1965-1987; 1998; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Royalty statements, Random House, 1976-1978 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Manuscripts
  - Aftosa, undated; typescript carbon with corrections (Box 11)
  - Artra, typescript with corrections (Box 12)
    See also Notebooks: Artra notes.
  - [on Baudelaire], handwritten with corrections (Box 12)
  - Book review, La France by Larousse, typescript carbon with corrections (Box 12)
  - Book review, Vanna by Emmanuelle Arsan (Box 12)
  - Book review, unidentified book by Daniel Guerin, typescript carbon with corrections (Box 12)
  - [on Camus and Faulkner], typescript; typescript carbon; both with corrections (Box 12)
  - Cesaire to Maurice Thoux, Secretary General of French Communist Party, handwritten with corrections (Box 12)
  - A Chronicle, 1956; typescript with corrections (Box 12)
  - Comment on the effect of pornographic readings on three persons; cast Don, Dick me (Box 12)
  - Epithalamion (Box 12)
  - Gilles de Rais Introduction Part Two: The historical evidence, 2 folders; see also (Box 12)
    See also Translations: Trial of Gilles de Rais.
  - Hannah, typescript (Box 12)
  - Hedyphagetica, 1954; typescript carbon with corrections (Box 12)
  - In Stockholm, spiral notebook with handwritten notes; typescript with corrections (Box 12)
  - Interrogations, handwritten volume (Box 13)
  - Klieje, from A Chroncle of Ghent, typescript (Box 13)
  - Letter to a communist, handwritten with corrections (Box 13)
  - The Medusa's petrifying gaze, appears to be an essay on Sartre; typescript with corrections (Box 13)
  - Memoir - Notes, handwritten notes, photocopied notes, clippings (Box 13)
    See also Translations: My Mother in which the piece appeared.
  - [on Negroness], possibly related to Congress of Negro Intellectuals; handwritten with corrections (Box 13)
  - Nicholas in Byzantz [Byzantium], typescript with corrections, two drafts (Box 13)
  - Notes on the situtation of the writer, typescript with corrections (Box 13)
  - Pneu crevé en Auvergne, script for short film, with Jacques Gauthier; typescript and typescript carbon, multiple drafts; letter from "Mike" with his evaluation (Box 13)
  - [on Presénce Africaine], typescript carbon with corrections (Box 13)
  - Prince of Janitzio, typescript (Box 13)
  - Sketches for an apology, 1951; typescript carbon (Box 13)
  - There came a youth, 2 folders; typescript (Box 13)
  - The undeveloped heart: E.M. Forster, 1948; AW's thesis; typescript carbon (Box 14)
  - Fragments (Box 14)
  - Translations
    - List of translations by AW, includes those done under pseudonym Pieralessandro Casavini (Box 14)
    - Les annees profonde, by Jouve, appears to have been a team effort, possibly student work?; typescripts, carbons with corrections (Box 14)
    - L'Arrete de mort, by Blanchot, photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 14)
    - L'Atelier d'Alberto Giacometti, author unknown, handwritten (Box 14)
    - C'est la guerre, by Calaferte, notebook, handwritten (Box 14)
    - Chance and necessity, by Monod, typescript carbon, photocopies; includes photographs for illustrations (Box 14)
    - Chine d'hier et d'aujourd'hui [excerpt] (Box 14)
    - Comment les riches detruisent la planete, by Kempf, photocopy of corrected handwritten manuscript; see also (Box 14)
      See also Correspondence: Chelsea Green Publishing.
    - Excerpt from the memoirs of la comtesse de C+++ relative to the author of "Gamiani", typescript with corrections (Box 14)
    - Expliquez-moil'existentialisme, by Campbell, typescript carbon (Box 14)
    - Francois, encore un effort..., handwritten with corrections (Box 14)
    - Les guerres sont loin [Lucien's story], by Kroh, notebook, handwritten (Box 15)
    - Les larmes d'Eros, by Bataille, 1961; typescript carbon with corrections (Box 15)
    - Letter to my comrades on the left, by Accardo, numerous drafts, handwritten and typescript; one folder of correspondence with various people including Virgil Burnett; 6 folders (Box 15)
    - Marino Marini, by Waldberg, typescript carbon in French, typescript in English with corrections; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - My mother, by Bataille, 2 folders; includes "Memoir" by AW and other pieces (Box 15)
      See also Memoir - Notes, above
    - Sarpedon[?], typescript with corrections (Box 15)
    - Thomas l'obscur, by Blanchot, typescript with corrections (Box 15)
    - Trial of Gilles de Rais, typescripts with corrections, multiple drafts; see also Gilles de Rais Introduction Part Two: The historical evidence, above; 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, fragments, translations by others, etc.
    - Books in my life, by Henry Miller, 1952; published in Points 15 (Box 16)
    - Desert world, by Pierre Jean Jouve, translated by Lydia Davis, typescript (Box 16)
    - Excerpts of others' work, Brecht, Chaucer (Box 16)